{"tossups": [{"question": "The timetable of this event had to be hurried after the central figure announced his plans to invade Parthia, and it began with a petition to recall the brother of Lucius Tillius Cimber. A series of bad dreams led Calpurnia to nearly prevent this event, which was organized by two men immortalized in Dante\u2019s ninth circle of Hell, Cassius and Brutus. For ten points, name this event that took place in 44 BC on the Ides of March and resulted in the death of a Roman dictator.", "answer": "<b> assassination of</b> Gaius Julius<b> Caesar</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "This modern-day country\u2019s intelligentsia were purged in Operation Searchlight. One politician from this country called for \u201cevery house to turn into a fortress\u201d after an electoral victory by the Awami League. This country\u2019s independence was guaranteed as part of the Simla Agreement. In 2013, the deadliest collapse due to structural failure occurred in this country after the collapse of the Rana Plaza. For ten points, name this country formerly known as East Pakistan, whose capital is Dhaka.", "answer": "<b> Bangladesh</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This city is home to an oak tree whose destruction was prevented by the Tercio of Bego\u02dcna. One event in this city took place on a Monday, its traditional market day, which increased casualty counts. George Steer wrote a report about the destruction of this city, which was carried out by Hugo Sperrle\u2019s Aviazione Legionaria. Operation Rugen targeted, for ten points, what Basque city whose bombing by the Condor Legion during the Spanish Civil War inspired a massive Pablo Picasso painting?", "answer": "<b> Guernica</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s subjects imposed the \u201cCharter of Privileges\u201d while this man was away in England, and he lost most of his territory to Philip Ford. This man wrote the book<em> No Cross, No Crown</em> while imprisoned in the Tower of London. New Castle was the capital of one his territories, which he almost named \u201cNew Wales\u201d until the intervention of the king. James II granted Delaware to this man, who was also granted a colony named for his family by Charles II in exchange for a fifth of all gold and silver. For ten points, name this man who founded a religious haven for Quakers.", "answer": "William<b> Penn</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Erawan Shrine is located in this city, whose temple of Wrat Pha Kaew houses the Emerald Buddha. This city was first founded as a trading post of the Ayyuthaya kingdom, though it has grown to include modern day attractions like the Patpong district and Khaosan Road. Located in the Chao Phraya River delta, this city was rocked in 2015 when bombs exploded at the Siam Paragon mall and nearby religious shrines. King Rama IX Park is located in, for ten points, what capital city of Thailand?", "answer": "<b> Bangkok</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "Unity College in Maine currently owns and uses a set of solar panels that this building had installed in the 1970s. For \u201cexercise and amusement\u201d at this location, a billiards table was controversially purchased for $61 in 1825. In 2011, a resident of this location started homebrewing a Honey Ale, using honey from beehives on the South Lawn. After learning that they would move to this location, Malia and Sasha got a new dog, Bo. For ten points, name this residence at 1600 Pennsylvania Avenue whose occupants have included Jimmy Carter and Barack Obama.", "answer": "<b> White House</b> <b>Second Quarter</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Misc Arts"}, {"question": "One of these weapons, called the<em> Galena</em>, assisted in the Siege of Fort Morgan. John Pope retreated after one of these weapons rammed the Richmond at the Battle of the Head of Passes. Catesby ap Roger Jones commanded one of these vessels after the wounding of Franklin Buchanan, following which the CSA began producing these ships. For ten points, name this type of ship, represented at Hampton Roads by the CSS<em> Virginia</em> and the USS<em> Monitor</em>, a heavily armored steamship with plating of a namesake metal.", "answer": "<b> ironclad</b>s (prompt on ships and other general terms)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "One member of this dynasty was killed by his guard Martialis while he was urinating on the roadside. The ascension of Macrinus interrupted this dynasty that ended when the coronation of Maximinus Thrax began the \u201cCrisis of the 3rd Century.\u201d One member of this dynasty caused a stir when he married a Vestal virgin. This dynasty included Geta and Elegabalus and was established following the defeats of Pescennius Niger and Clodius Albinus in the Year of the Five Emperors. For ten points, name this Roman dynasty that was founded by the North African Septimius.", "answer": "<b> Severan</b> dynasty", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "The term \u201ccold war\u201d was coined by this man in his work \u201cYou and the Atomic Bomb.\u201d He described working class attitudes towards socialism in<em> The Road to Wigan Pier</em> and documented the Spanish Civil War in another work. In<em> Burmese Days</em>, this man recounted the necessity of upholding his reputation by shooting an elephant. A pig named Napoleon features in an allegorical work by this man, who also wrote Winston Smith\u2019s life under Big Brother. For ten points, name this dystopian author of<em> Animal Farm</em> and <em>1984</em>.", "answer": "George<b> Orwell</b>", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Misc Literature"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "A form of protest known as the teach-in originated at this university. Alan Haber founded the left-wing student activist group Students for a Democratic Society at this university. John F. Kennedy announced his plan for the Peace Corps while speaking at this university, where Lyndon B. Johnson outlined the Great Society. This school lost the case<em> Gratz v. Bollinger</em>, which questioned its racial affirmative action policies. For ten points, name this flagship state university located in Ann Arbor.", "answer": "University of<b> Michigan</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Regis Debray formulated the idea of<em> foco</em> based on the experiences of this man. This man\u2019s admiration for Patrice Lumumba led him to assist Laurent-Desire Kabila in the Simba Rebellion. Alberto Korta captured the most famous image of this man during a memorial service for the<em> La Coubre</em> explosion. After the failure of the Bay of Pigs invasion, this man wrote a thank you letter to John F. Kennedy. For ten points, name this man, whose \u201cHeroic Guerrilla Fighter\u201d portrait has become a revolutionary symbol.", "answer": "Ernesto \u201c<b>Che</b>\u201d<b> Guevara</b> (accept either name; accept Ernesto<b> Lynch</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "One side in this conflict established its naval superiority following the Battle of the Downs. Frederick Henry lost support in this conflict following his defeat at Kallo, and the Twelve Years Truce was broken by the Duke of Olivares in this conflict. The Sea Beggers participated in this conflict that was ended by the Treaty of Munster, and Diego Velasquez painted a depiction of this conflict\u2019s siege of Breda. William the Silent brought the House of Orange to prominence in, for ten points, what lengthy conflict for Dutch independence from Spain?", "answer": "<b> Eighty Years War</b> (or the<b> Dutch War of Independence</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>The North American Martyrs were born in this country and ritually killed by Native Americans. Another man born in this country, Father Sebastian Rale, was killed during</b> <b>Dummer\u2019s War. Though the (+)</b> <b>Kirke brothers were born in this country, they captured</b> <b>one of its New World colonies for England during the Thirty Years\u2019 War. The Third Treaty of San (*) </b> Ildefonso granted this country territory that, three years later, it sold to America for $15 million. For ten points, name this European country that colonized Quebec under Samuel de Champlain and founded New Orleans during Louis XV\u2019s reign.", "answer": "Kingdom of<b> France</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>A carving of Christ accompanied by an inscription in these characters commemorate the deeds of Gorm the Old and Harald Bluetooth in a pair of historical records from (+) Jelling [yelling]. A sample of this script commemorates the king of Hreidsea [h-RYED-say-uh], Theodoric, and was recovered from a church wall in R\u00a8ok. The \u201clong (*) </b> branch\u201d and \u201cshort twig\u201d versions of this script are contrasted with the H\u00a8alsinge [HEL-sing-uh] ones, which lack staves and are part of the Younger Futhark form of this alphabet that is commonly found throughout Sweden and Norway. For ten points, name this Germanic alphabet recorded on namesake stones.", "answer": "Scandinavian<b> rune</b>s (accept younger<b> futhark</b> or younger<b> futhork</b> until it is read; do not accept \u201celder futhark\u201d)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>In this city, Operation Wotan was launched in an attempt to break the Mozhaisk defense line. Fedor von Bock attempted to capture this city shortly after the battles of Minsk and</b> <b>Smolensk. Though this city was besieged, Stalin ordered that the annual (+)</b> <b>Revolution</b> <b>Day parade be held regardless in order to raise morale. Operation Typhoon targeted this city, which was reinforced by Georgy Zhukov, who directed the (*)</b> Victory Parade here. During the siege of this city, troops from Army Group Centre could reportedly see, but would not reach, the spires of the Kremlin. The Nazis did not capture, for ten points, what capital of the USSR?", "answer": "<b> Moscow</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}], "bonuses": []}